Preliminary Inventory of the Mariia Feodorovna, Empress, Consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia, Letters to Queen Alexandra
Hoover Institution Archives
Mariia Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia, letters to Queen Alexandra,
1881-1925
76097
Mariia Feodorovna, Empress, consort of Alexander III, Emperor of Russia, 1847-1928
16 manuscript boxes (6.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Letters to Queen Alexandra of Great Britain. Relates to matters of state and family.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (16 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
Letters to Queen Alexandra of Great Britain. Relates to matters of state and family.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Romanov, House of.; Great Britain.; Great Britain--Court and courtiers.; Russia.; Russia--Court and courtiers.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1844-1925.
Container List
- Letters (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1881 April 8, 10
  - 1890
    - September 18 (Folder 1: 2)
    - December 7 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1891 May 29 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1892
    - March 6 (Folder 1: 5)
    - April 20 (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1893
    - March 5 (Folder 1: 7)
    - December 8 (Folder 1: 8)
  - 1894
    - 1894 April 11, 22 (Folder 1: 9)
    - May 7, 21 (Folder 1: 10)
    - September 22 (Folder 1: 11)
    - October 5, 15 (Folder 1: 12)
  - 1895
    - January 6, 31 (Folder 1: 13)
    - February 6 (Folder 1: 14)
    - March 6, 23 (Folder 1: 15)
    - April 18 (Folder 1: 16)
    - May 13 (Folder 1: 17)
    - June 20 (Folder 1: 18)
    - July 19 (Folder 1: 19)
    - October 22 (Folder 1: 20)
    - November 6, 12 (Folder 1: 21)
    - December 7 (Folder 1: 22)
  - 1896
    - January 10 (Folder 1: 23)
    - February 2, 18 (Folder 1: 24)
    - May 4, 28 (Folder 1: 25)
    - September 14 (Folder 1: 26)
    - October 3 (Folder 1: 27)
  - 1897
    - September 28, 29 (Folder 1: 28)
    - October 3, 18 (Folder 1: 29)
    - November 10 (Folder 1: 30)
    - December 7, 18 (Folder 1: 31)
  - 1898 April 15 (Folder 1: 32)
  - 1899
    - February 19 (Folder 1: 33)
    - June 21 (Folder 1: 34)
    - December 27 (Folder 1: 35)
  - 1900
    - April 21, 29 (Folder 1: 36)
    - May 6, 13, 27 (Folder 1: 37)
    - June 3, 10, 18, 24, 30 (Folder 1: 38)
    - July 8, 14, 19, 25, 29 (Folder 1: 39)
    - October 12, 21, 28 (Folder 1: 40)
    - November 4, 10, 23 (Folder 1: 41)
    - December 1, 5, 22, 30 (Folder 1: 42)
  - 1901 (Box 2)
    - January 5, 11, 16, 18, 26 (Folder 2: 1)
    - February 3, 12 (Folder 2: 2)
    - April 4, 11, 14, 20, 30 (Folder 2: 3)
    - May 14 (Folder 2: 4)
    - June 13 (Folder 2: 5)
    - July 1, 14 (Folder 2: 6)
    - September 11, 19, 24 (Folder 2: 7)
    - October 2, 10, 16 (Folder 2: 8)
    - November 6 (Folder 2: 9)
    - December 1, 13, 21, 26 (Folder 2: 10)
  - 1902
    - June 15 (Folder 2: 11)
    - July 4, 12 (Folder 2: 12)
    - October 12, 18, 24, 29 (Folder 2: 13)
    - November 8, 15, 29 (Folder 2: 14)
    - December 6, 28 (Folder 2: 15)
  - 1903
    - January 10 (Folder 2: 16)
    - February 20 (Folder 2: 17)
    - March 7 (Folder 2: 18)
    - April 24, 25 (Folder 2: 19)
    - June 18, 23 (Folder 2: 20)
    - November 6, 29 (Folder 2: 21)
    - December 7 (Folder 2: 22)
  - 1904
    - February 13, 22, 28 (Folder 2: 23)
    - March 9, 27 (Folder 2: 24)
    - April 9 (Folder 2: 25)
    - July 24 (Folder 2: 26)
    - September 8 (Folder 2: 27)
    - October 22 (Folder 2: 28)
    - November 8 (Folder 2: 29)
    - December 3, 7 (Folder 2: 30)
  - 1905
    - January 3, 19, 30 (Folder 2: 31)
    - February 6, 14 (Folder 2: 32)
    - May 1 (Folder 2: 33)
    - June 7 (Folder 2: 34)
    - July 18 (Folder 2: 35)
    - August 17 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - October 3, 14, 22, 25 (Folder 3: 2)
    - November 4, 10, 23, 30 (Folder 3: 3)
    - December 14, 26, 31 (Folder 3: 4)
  - 1906
    - February 20, 28 (Folder 3: 5)
    - March 13, 24 (Folder 3: 6)
    - April 24 (Folder 3: 7)
    - June 25 (Folder 3: 8)
    - July 10, 19 (Folder 3: 9)
    - October 13, 19, 23, 26, 30 (Folder 3: 10)
    - November 3, 5, 10, 13, 21, 22, 29 (Folder 3: 11)
    - December 1, 2, 12, 13, 18, 22, 26, 29 (Folder 3: 12)
  - 1907
    - January 3, 25, 31 (postcard) (Folder 3: 13)
    - February 6 (Folder 3: 14)
    - March 3 (Folder 3: 15)
    - April 7, 8, 9, 11, 16, 18, 23 (Folder 3: 16)
    - May 4, 12, 29 (Folder 3: 17)
    - June 3 (Folder 3: 18)
    - July 2, 8, 12 (telegram), 30 (Folder 3: 19)
    - October 26 (Folder 3: 20)
    - November 1 (2 letters), 9, 19, 29 (Folder 3: 21)
    - December 3, 4, 7, 14, 26, 30 (Folder 3: 22)
  - 1908 (Box 4)
    - January 21, 23, 25 (Folder 4: 1)
    - February 9 (Folder 4: 2)
    - April 19, 22 (Folder 4: 3)
    - May 7, 29 (Folder 4: 4)
    - June 9, 15 (Folder 4: 5)
    - July 16, 25 (Folder 4: 6)
    - August 2 (Folder 4: 7)
    - November 4, 13, 16, 18, 23 (Folder 4: 8)
    - December 1, 7, 29 (Folder 4: 9)
  - 1909
    - January 14, 26 (Folder 4: 10)
    - February 3, 13 (Folder 4: 11)
    - March 28 (Folder 4: 12)
    - May 14, 25 (Folder 4: 13)
    - June 1, 15 (Folder 4: 14)
    - July 3, 9, 11, 19 (Folder 4: 15)
    - August 2, 14 (Folder 4: 16)
    - October 30 (Folder 4: 17)
    - November 3, 10, 13, 17, 24, 29 (Folder 4: 18)
    - December 10, 16, 20, 27, 30 (Folder 4: 19)
  - 1910
    - January 4, 21, 29 (Folder 4: 20)
    - February 8, 20 (Folder 4: 21)
    - March 7, 10, 31 (Folder 4: 22)
    - April 1, 21 (Folder 4: 23)
    - May 7 (Folder 4: 24)
    - August 17 (Folder 4: 25)
    - November 21, 24, 28 (Folder 4: 26)
    - December 1, 5, 27 (Folder 4: 27)
  - 1911 (Box 5)
    - January 3, 23 (Folder 5: 1)
    - February 6, 15, 23 (Folder 5: 2)
    - March 6, 16 (Folder 5: 3)
    - April 3 (Folder 5: 4)
    - May 2, 4, 7, 13, 18 (Folder 5: 5)
    - June 12 (Folder 5: 6)
    - October 20, 26, 31 (Folder 5: 7)
    - November 14, 18, 22 (Folder 5: 8)
    - December 21, 26, 29, 30 (Folder 5: 9)
  - 1912
    - January 18 (Folder 5: 10)
    - February 10, 22 (Folder 5: 11)
    - March 2, 11, 13 (Folder 5: 12)
    - April 1, 12 (Folder 5: 13)
    - June 2, 9, 16 (Folder 5: 14)
    - July 3, 19 (Folder 5: 15)
    - August 12 (Folder 5: 16)
    - November 5, 13, 29 (Folder 5: 17)
    - December 1 (2 letters), 7, 20, 31 (Folder 5: 18)
  - 1913
    - January 16, 27 (Folder 5: 19)
    - February 5, 29 (Folder 5: 20)
    - March 11, 31 (Folder 5: 21)
    - April 9, 10 (Folder 5: 22)
    - October 10, 13, 20, 24, 29 (Folder 5: 23)
    - November 8, 13, 20, 28 (Folder 5: 24)
    - December 1, 11, 21, 23, 25, 27 (Folder 5: 25)
  - 1914 (Box 6)
    - January 7, 21 (Folder 6: 1)
    - February 1, 3, 7, 16, 24 (Folder 6: 2)
    - March 7, 28 (Folder 6: 3)
    - April 8 (Folder 6: 4)
    - August 2, 5, 20 (Folder 6: 5)
    - September 7, 23 (Folder 6: 6)
    - October 8, 14, 19, 19 (Folder 6: 7)
    - November 2, 4, 23, 30 (Folder 6: 8)
    - December 5, 13, 23, 30 (Folder 6: 9)
  - 1915
    - January 4, 21 (Folder 6: 10)
    - February 24 (Folder 6: 11)
    - March 3, 16, 22, 26, 31 (Folder 6: 12)
    - April 2 (Folder 6: 13)
    - August 5, 19, 24 (Folder 6: 14)
    - September 1, 6, 12, 17, 25, 29 (Folder 6: 15)
    - October 11, 13 (Folder 6: 16)
    - November 2, 13, 25 (Folder 6: 17)
    - December 1, 9, 17, 22 (Folder 6: 18)
  - 1916 (Box 7)
    - January 2, 10, 16, 26 (Folder 7: 1)
    - February 7, 13, 14, 15, 21 (Folder 7: 2)
    - March 3, 8, 11, 14, 18, 23, 29 (Folder 7: 3)
    - April 5, 7, 12, 19, 24, 29 (Folder 7: 4)
    - May 7, 12, 18, 29 (Folder 7: 5)
    - June 2, 9, 13, 24 (Folder 7: 6)
    - July 2, 7, 13, 20, 24, 27 (Folder 7: 7)
    - August 3, 9, 14, 21, 25, 31 (Folder 7: 8)
    - September 3, 9, 14, 18, 24 (Folder 7: 9)
    - October 2, 5, 9, 15, 23, 25 (Folder 7: 10)
    - November 2, 6, 15, 23 (Folder 7: 11)
  - 1918
    - August 14 (Folder 7: 12)
    - September 9, 23 (Folder 7: 13)
    - October 12 (Folder 7: 14)
    - November 8, 17, 26 (Folder 7: 15)
    - December 10, 16, 24, 29 (Folder 7: 16)
  - 1919 (Box 8)
    - January 24 (Folder 8: 1)
    - February 1, 10, 19 (Folder 8: 2)
    - March 4, 14, 15, 19, 29 (Folder 8: 3)
    - April 2, 28, 29 (Folder 8: 4)
    - September 1, 6, 13, 19, 22, 24 (Folder 8: 5)
    - October 4 (2 letters with same date?), 8, 19, 27, 30 (Folder 8: 6)
    - November 2, 6, 10, 12, 18, 20, 23, 29 (Folder 8: 7)
    - December 1, 5, 8, 11, 15, 18, 22, 26, 29 (Folder 8: 8)
  - 1920
    - January 1, 6, 12, 16, 19, 22, 25(?), 29 (Folder 8: 9)
    - February 1, 2, 5, 8, 13, 15, 19, 23, 27 (Folder 8: 10)
    - March 1, 5, 8, 12, 15, 19, 24, 26, 29 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - April 1, 6, 10, 12, 17, 21, 24, 27 (Folder 9: 2)
    - May
      - 1, 4, 6, 8 (2 letters), 12, 14, 17, 19 (Folder 9: 3)
      - 21 (2 letters), 23, 25, 27, 28, 29, 30 (Folder 9: 4)
    - June
      - 2, 3, 6, 8 (2 letters), 11, 13 (Folder 9: 5)
      - 15, 18, 19, 22, 24, 26, 28 (Folder 9: 6)
    - July 5, 8, 10, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 30 (Folder 9: 7)
    - August
      - 1, 5, 10, 13, 16, 18 (Folder 9: 8)
      - 20, 23, 25, 27, 30 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - September
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 13, 15 (Folder 10: 2)
      - 17, 20, 22, 24, 25, 27, 29 (Folder 10: 3)
    - October
      - 1, 4, 5, 9, 11, 12, 15 (Folder 10: 4)
      - 18, 20, 22, 23, 25, 27, 29 (Folder 10: 5)
    - November
      - 1, 2, 5, 8, 10, 13 (Folder 10: 6)
      - 18, 22, 24, 26, 27, 29 (Folder 10: 7)
    - December
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 11, 14 (2 letters) (Folder 10: 8)
      - 18, 20, 22, 25, 27, 29 (Folder 10: 9)
  - 1921 (Box 11)
    - January
      - 1, 3, 5, 8, 10, 11, 15 (Folder 11: 1)
      - 17, 19, 21, 24, 26, 28 (Folder 11: 2)
    - February
      - 2, 5, 8, 9, 11, 16 (Folder 11: 3)
      - 19, 21, 23, 25, 28 (Folder 11: 4)
    - March
      - 2, 4, 8, 9, 12, 14 (Folder 11: 5)
      - 16, 18, 21, 23, 25, 29, 30 (Folder 11: 6)
    - April
      - 2, 4, 6, 9, 10, 13 (Folder 11: 7)
      - 16, 18, 20, 23(?), 27, 30 (Folder 11: 8)
    - May
      - 3, 4, 5, 8, 10, 12, 16 (Folder 11: 9)
      - 17, 18, 22, 24, 27, 29 (Folder 11: 10)
    - June
      - 1, 3, 5, 7, 8, 11 (Folder 11: 11)
      - 14, 16, 20, 21, 23, 27 (Folder 11: 12)
    - July (Box 12)
      - 1, 3, 5, 7, 11, 12 (Folder 12: 1)
      - 14, 18, 22, 25, 26, 29 (Folder 12: 2)
    - August
      - 1, 5, 8, 9, 12, 15, 16 (Folder 12: 3)
      - 19, 21, 23, 26, 28, 30 (Folder 12: 4)
    - September
      - 2(?), 5, 6, 9, 11, 13, 15 (Folder 12: 5)
      - 18, 19, 23, 26, 27, 30 (Folder 12: 6)
    - October
      - 2, 4, 7, 10, 11, 13 (Folder 12: 7)
      - 17, 20, 23, 24, 28, 30 (Folder 12: 8)
    - November
      - 1, 4, 7, 8, 10, 14, 15 (Folder 12: 9)
      - 17, 20, 22, 24, 28, 29 (Folder 12: 10)
    - December
      - 1, 5, 6, 9, 11, 13, 16 (Folder 12: 11)
      - 19, 22, 26, 27, 29 (Folder 12: 12)
  - 1922 (Box 13)
    - January
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 12 (Folder 13: 1)
      - 15, 17, 20, 23, 24, 27, 29 (Folder 13: 2)
    - February 5, 9 (Folder 13: 3)
    - March 3, 6, 10, 12, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 28, 31 (Folder 13: 4)
    - April
      - 3, 4, 7, 10 (2 letters), 14 (Folder 13: 5)
      - 17, 18, 20, 24, 25, 28 (Folder 13: 6)
    - May
      - 1, 2, 4, 8, 9, 11, 15 (Folder 13: 7)
      - 16, 18, 21, 22, 25, 29, 30 (Folder 13: 8)
    - June
      - 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 13, 18 (Folder 13: 9)
      - 20, 23, 25, 27, 30, 30 (Folder 13: 10)
    - July 3, 7, 9, 11, 14, 16, 18, 20, 23, 28, 31 (Folder 13: 11)
    - August
      - 1, 4, 6, 8, 11, 14, 15 (Folder 13: 12)
      - 18, 21, 22, 24, 28, 29 (Folder 13: 13)
    - September
      - 1, 3, 5, 7, 11, 12 (Folder 14: 1)
      - 16, 18, 20, 25, 26, 28 (Folder 14: 2)
    - October
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 16 (Folder 14: 3)
      - 20, 22, 24, 27, 29, 31 (Folder 14: 4)
    - November 2, 6 (2 letters), 9, 13, 17, 20 (Folder 14: 5)
  - 1923
    - August 27 (Folder 14: 6)
    - September 7, 13, 17 (Folder 14: 7)
    - October 2, 15, 19, 21, 30 (Folder 14: 8)
    - November 3, 5, 13, 17, 20, 23, 28 (Folder 14: 9)
    - December 2, 6, 14, 20, 26, 31 (Folder 14: 10)
  - 1924
    - January 2, 5, 7, 9 (2 letters), 15, 18, 20, 24, 29 (Folder 14: 11)
    - February 4, 12, 18, 19, 22, 25, 29 (Folder 14: 12)
    - March
      - 3, 7, 11, 14, 16 (Folder 14: 13)
      - 20, 21, 23, 24, 28, 30 (Folder 14: 14)
    - April
      - 1, 4, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 14 (Folder 14: 15)
      - 15, 17, 20, 22, 25, 27, 28 (Folder 14: 16)
    - May 2, 4, 6, 13, 16, 18, 20, 23, 25, 30 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - June
      - 1, 2, 6, 8, 10, 12 (Folder 15: 2)
      - 15, 17, 19, 23, 27, 28, 30 (Folder 15: 3)
    - July 4, 7, 11, 14, 16, 18, 22, 23, 25, 27, 30 (Folder 15: 4)
    - August
      - 1, 6, 8, 10, 13, 15 (Folder 15: 5)
      - 18, 19, 24, 26, 28, 29 (Folder 15: 6)
    - September
      - 1, 4, 5, 7, 9, 12, 14 (Folder 15: 7)
      - 16, 18, 19, 21, 23, 26, 29 (Folder 15: 8)
    - October
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 17 (Folder 15: 9)
      - 19, 20, 23, 26, 27, 29, 31 (Folder 15: 10)
    - November
      - 2, 4, 7, 9, 11, 14 (Folder 15: 11)
      - 16, 18, 21, 23, 25, 30 (Folder 15: 12)
    - December 1 (Folder 15: 13)
  - 1925
    - January 9, 16, 18, 27, 31 (Folder 15: 14)
    - February 6, 9, 16, 21, 24, 27 (Folder 15: 15)
    - March (Box 16)
      - 2, 6, 8, 10, 14, 16 (Folder 16: 1)
      - 17, 20, 24, 29, 31 (Folder 16: 2)
    - April 6, 10, 13, 16, 20, 24, 25, 28 (Folder 16: 3)
    - May
      - 1, 3, 6, 8, 10, 15 (Folder 16: 4)
      - 17, 19, 25, 29, 31 (Folder 16: 5)
    - June 3, 7, 12, 14, 19, 21, 26, 28 (Folder 16: 6)
    - July
      - 3, 5, 8, 10, 12, 14 (Folder 16: 7)
      - 19, 22, 24, 26, 29, 31 (Folder 16: 8)
    - August 2, 7, 9, 14, 17, 19, 23, 28, 30 (Folder 16: 9)
    - September 2, 4, 8, 11, 13, 15, 20, 24, 28 (Folder 16: 10)
    - October 2, 5, 8, 12, 15, 19, 25, 28 (Folder 16: 11)
    - November 1, 5, 8, 11, 15 (Folder 16: 12)
- Newspaper issue - Philadelphia Record, 1945 April 13 (Folder 16: 13)
- Telegrams, 1919 (Folder 16: 14)